<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Marissa Phul | Software Engineer - Portfolio]]></title><description><![CDATA[portfolio and blog.]]></description><link>http://mphul.codes</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:54:34 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Black Lives Matter. Every single day.]]></title><description><![CDATA[I have a lot to say but now is not the time for my voice. Every day we should be amplifying and giving space to Black voices but especially…]]></description><link>http://mphul.codes/black-lives-matter/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://mphul.codes/black-lives-matter/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to say but now is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the time for my voice. Every day we should be amplifying and giving space to Black voices but especially now because the movement has more momentum than it has had since the 60s and 70s. Keep that energy going. Liberation happens collectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some of my favourite articles/blog posts from Black voices. The list will be constantly updated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/defund-police-canada-black-indigenous-lives_ca_5ed65eb2c5b6ccd7c56bdf7d&quot;&gt;Defunding The Police Will Save Black And Indigenous Lives In Canada&lt;/a&gt; - Sandy Hudson, June 2 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/opinion/contributors/2020/06/02/for-black-people-calling-the-police-can-be-dangerous-its-time-we-had-another-option.html&quot;&gt;For Black people calling the police can be dangerous. It’s time we had another option&lt;/a&gt; - Angelyn Francis, June 3 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/opinion/contributors/2020/05/29/its-long-past-time-to-talk-about-policing-of-black-women-in-canada.html&quot;&gt;It’s long-past time to talk about policing of Black women in Canada&lt;/a&gt; - Robyn Maynard, May 29 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ricochet.media/en/3163/why-black-canadians-dont-believe-trudeau-and-canada&quot;&gt;Why Black Canadians don’t believe Trudeau and Canada&lt;/a&gt; - Hawa Mire, June 3  2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://truthout.org/articles/police-reforms-you-should-always-oppose/&quot;&gt;Police “Reforms” You Should Always Oppose&lt;/a&gt; - Mariame Kaba, December 7 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vulture.com/2020/06/anti-racist-reading-lists-what-are-they-for.html?&quot;&gt;What Is an Anti-Racist Reading List For?&lt;/a&gt; - Lauren Michele Jackson, June 4 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vogue.co.uk/arts-and-lifestyle/article/performative-grief-online&quot;&gt;We Need To Rethink Our “Pics Or It Didn’t Happen” Approach To Activism&lt;/a&gt; - Yomi Adegoke, June 2 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/opinion/star-columnists/2018/03/28/systemic-racism-in-canada-is-real-folks.html&quot;&gt;Systemic racism in Canada is real, folks&lt;/a&gt; - Vicky Mochama, March 28 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-country/country-music-racist-history-1010052/&quot;&gt;Rewriting Country Music’s Racist History&lt;/a&gt; - Elamin Abdelmahmoud, June 5 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/04/17/magazine/prison-abolition-ruth-wilson-gilmore.html&quot;&gt;Is Prison Necessary? Ruth Wilson Gilmore Might Change Your Mind&lt;/a&gt; - Rachel Kushner, April 17 2019&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The future of interaction: Tech vs the People]]></title><description><![CDATA[Like all of us, I’ve been spending a lot of time online during the coronavirus pandemic. As companies announce permanent remote-first work…]]></description><link>http://mphul.codes/future-of-interaction/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://mphul.codes/future-of-interaction/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Like all of us, I’ve been spending a lot of time online during the coronavirus pandemic. As companies announce permanent remote-first work or pivot their strategies to increase online engagement, I’ve watched with great interest the multitude of “hot takes” that have overtaken my twitter feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was struck by an interesting juxtaposition: despite an explosion of voices calling to move more of our activity online, &lt;strong&gt;people keep showing us that they want in-person interactions&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not here to put forth my idea of a new type of communication or talk about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; people are ignoring social distancing rules. In this post, I will outline what I see as a conflict between tech company’s view of human interaction and the general publics’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Tech&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter and Shopify recently announced that they would be moving to a permanent remote-first strategy. Companies should absolutely be remote-friendly. Accessibility is something the tech industry is severely lacking in both product and culture. However, does this mean we put everything online?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech companies are not just pivoting to remote work, they’re focusing on remote products. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why go to your friend’s house for a movie night when you can stay in your own house and use Netflix Party? Why meet for coffee when you can hop onto Houseparty or Clubhouse? Why go for a hike when you can ride together on Peleton?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech is the one industry where close physical proximity has consistently bred innovation. Google, Apple, Microsoft, and many others were started in a garage. Larry Page and Sergey Brin worked day and night, they were basically living together. Today, incubators litter San Francisco and like-minded people live in co-ops and houses together. The city itself is a textbook example of how people in close-proximity can create ideas and generate a pool of talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re constantly trying to monetize human interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless we start charging people for going on a hike in a public park or for both coffee &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the table you sit at, it’s &lt;strong&gt;easier to monetize online&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The People&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of social interaction for healthy brain &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627315007795#bib77&quot;&gt;function&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3308644/&quot;&gt;development&lt;/a&gt;, physical &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/newsletter_article/the-health-benefits-of-strong-relationships&quot;&gt;health&lt;/a&gt; and happiness cannot be overstated. So you may ask, is it possible to replicate this online? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no better test than the pandemic we are currently facing. In order to get the in-person human interaction we desire, people would have to risk contracting a lethal virus. Hoards of people are flocking to beaches, and even before the warm weather hit, they were finding ways to meet for walks or hang out in their friend’s basement. People desire human contact enough to risk contracting a deadly virus in exchange for one hour outside with an acquaintance. Think back to the videos that circulated in April of spring breakers; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CBSNews/status/1240371160078000128&quot;&gt;“If I get corona, I get corona. At the end of the day, I’m not gonna let it stop me from partying.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are social beings, and that doesn’t just mean hanging out with friends, it means we work, organize, exchange, create, and govern together. Can we replicate all those functions to the same degree of satisfaction and success that we do (or can do) in person?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think so and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S074756321000213X&quot;&gt;science&lt;/a&gt; doesn’t think so either. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/1800307/why-person-socializing-mandatory-do-item&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent article talking about the importance of exchanging ideas and working physically together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I miss the most since the beginning of quarantine? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Micro-interactions that make me feel like part of the broader world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My daily visit to the coffee shop down the street. I can make coffee at home or I can use the Starbucks app to pre-order. But that has not fulfilled my desire. I miss my conversation with the barista who knows I like an extra hot Americano with no room. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going to the grocery store. I can get groceries delivered but does it replicate walking around the store aimlessly or having an impulse for fresh pasta and heading over after work for a two-item purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chatting with random people in lines. I compliment their tote bag, them my shirt. We smile and go our separate ways. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just in-person interaction, we also need the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a social species doesn’t just mean we desire gatherings like parties and festivals, it means that we also need the interaction we get &lt;strong&gt;every time we go out into the world&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;But doesn’t Gen Z live online?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/os_maris/status/1264661014718676995?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; that online connections are just as meaningful as in-person ones. I stand by this but my point in this post isn’t to claim that in-person interactions are more meaningful but that they are &lt;em&gt;preferred&lt;/em&gt; and even &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen Z lives online. I haven’t known a day without the internet. I spent a large chunk of my high school years snapchatting my friends in the same room as me. But what are we posting online? Photos of us sitting in our couch in the same sweatpants we wore to bed? Thoughts we had after spending all day indoors with our cat? No, photos of us &lt;em&gt;doing things&lt;/em&gt; and thoughts that were promoted from &lt;em&gt;talking to a random girl&lt;/em&gt; in the club bathroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We crave experiences. We want memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facetiming my friends is meaningful but it’s not an &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; and it’s not &lt;em&gt;postable&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A polaroid taken on some random person’s camera in a dark club dressed in a sparkly wrap dress, that is &lt;strong&gt;both&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why are we pushing people online post-coronavirus when we so clearly desire in-person communication? Would Tech’s time be better spent creating ways to make in-person communication more meaningful?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear your thoughts. Let me know on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/os_maris&quot;&gt;@os_maris&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lessons from using self-learned Golang in the workplace]]></title><description><![CDATA[When I was first learning Golang, I didn’t think I would be using it in the workplace just 4 months later. I’m still learning the language…]]></description><link>http://mphul.codes/golang-in-the-workplace/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://mphul.codes/golang-in-the-workplace/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When I was first learning Golang, I didn’t think I would be using it in the workplace just 4 months later. I’m still learning the language but I’d like to think I’m no longer a beginner. Just like applying skills from a degree to the workplace is different, so is applying self-learned skills. That’s why I wanted to take some time to share some of the ways my &lt;strong&gt;thinking shifted&lt;/strong&gt; once I started using Go in a professional environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Channels are king&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I viewed channels as a data transfer pipeline for &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;goroutines&lt;/code&gt;, allowing data to be written and read to. I was half right. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Channels should be thought of as a communication tool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Channels are about the transfer of information but not just data that you want to access in a different goroutine. It can be an alert. A channel, without a buffer, would only receive a message if there is an error thus notifying another goroutine that some part of the system/program has malfunctioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Channels are Go’s main synchronization mechanism. The standard library does have mutex for goroutine sync but channels are special. They block without explicit locks or condition variables. Synchronization and data transfer become one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. The standard library is enough&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Go, I’d primarily worked with Python and JavaScript. In these languages, most projects (right or wrong) have at least a few third-party dependencies. This isn’t the case with Go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go’s standard library is very robust. Aside from APIs, which I’ll talk about next, everything can be done with the standard library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was so used to outsourcing certain parts of my projects instead of looking in the language first. Go is very opinionated, there aren’t a hundred variations to write something, so you’re forced into following best practices. This means, you’re less likely to farm out work and if you do, you can be pretty confident in its integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Integrating with APIs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like so many, a lot of my work is with systems running in the cloud. Talking to AWS, was my first exposure to Go and APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned above, Go imposes/encourages a certain style without an actual style guide. Therefore, integrating with APIs is far more straightforward. You aren’t learning both the third-party system and their logic, just the system. The logic behind the APIs functions is so similar to yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. It’s all about concurrency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I truly grasped the importance of concurrency until I saw it applied in a distributed system. In my small project, concurrency wasn’t necessary but when you’re processing requests, making computations, and responding, concurrency is a must.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first read, one might assume concurrency and parallel programming are similar or even the same. However, concurrency is a programming paradigm. Concurrent programs can run in parallel, but they don’t have too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main benefit of concurrent programs is their ability to break up executions into different, independent tasks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goroutines run in the same memory space so the key to making this concurrent system work is synchronization. There is a myriad of ways to control synchronization however, channels are primarily used. See above for more on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a large system, functions heavily rely on shared data and when your system is distributed, managing access to that data is a challenge. Go helps make that easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What’s the number one lesson you learned when you applied your own skills in a professional environment? How is it different from learning on the job?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear your thoughts and stories. Let me know on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/os_maris&quot;&gt;@os_maris&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>